Preliminary Guide to the Engineering, Science, Management War Training Program Records, 1940 - 1945 UA.26.01.0003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Engineering, Science, and Management War Training Program records
1940 - 1945
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
United States. Office of Education
UA.26.01.0003
7.5 Linear Feet
The Engineering, Science, Management War Training (ESMWT) program trained students to participate in defense activities, in order to meet the shortage of engineers, chemists, physicists, and production supervisors during World War II. The Duke University ESMWT was administered by A. S. Brower, and was overseen by the United States Department of Education. The Engineering, Science, and Management War Training Program Records includes general information, forms, reports, bulletins, financial records, correspondence, and course material dating from 1940-1945. English.
7500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Engineering, Science, and Management War Training Program Records were acquired by the University Archives circa 1964.
Historical Note
The Engineering, Science, Management War Training (ESMWT) program was designed to provide short courses of college level to individuals who would be immediately available upon completion to participate in defense activities, in order to meet the shortage of engineers, chemists, physicists, and production supervisors in fields essential to national defense. Organized under the Labor-Federal Security Appropriation Act, 1944 (PL 135), and administered by the U.S. Office of Education, the program was coordinated by regional advisors, working with individual institutions. Duke University's institutional representative was A. S. Brower, Treasurer of the University at that time.
Each institution assumed full responsibility for administering its ESMWT program in full accordance with the provisions of its approved plan. This included seeking approval for and the teaching of courses, recruiting and selecting trainees, expenditure of funds, and keeping records and accounts.
All courses provided by the institutions involved were approved by the Office of Education, based on regional and national need for this training. These courses were intended to provide skills in specific activities of immediate application, rather than being part of a course of study. "Chemistry of Explosives" and "Engineering Drawing" were just two of the courses offered. ESMWT courses were provided without tuition or fees to qualified trainees, and often took place in off-campus locations in the surrounding region.
ESMWT was operated under several names, and was at first called Engineering Defense Training. At the beginning of the 1941-1942 program, the name was changed to the Engineering, Science, and Management Defense Training. It was later changed to theEngineering, Science, and Management War Training.
Collection Overview
The Engineering, Science, and Management War Training Program Records include general information, forms, reports, bulletins, financial records, and course material. Also included are correspondence and memos circulated among Duke University, the Office of Education, instructors, and trainees. The records date from 1940 to 1945, and are arranged in two series: General Information and Program Files.
Related Material
College Organization for General Service Records, 1940-1949
Duke University Archives
World War, 1939-1945 -- War work -- North Carolina; World War, 1939-1945 -- Education and the war; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work -- Schools; Science -- Study and teaching; Engineering -- Study and teaching -- United States; Brower, A. S. (Alfred Smith), 1892-1968; United States. Office of Education; United States. Office of Education; Duke University -- History; Duke University -- Students
- General Information
  Scope and Contents note
  The General Information series includes information relevant to the entire program, rather than to specific courses or program years.
  - Advertisements (Box 1)
  - Employment opportunities (Box 1)
  - Index of instructors' names (Box 1)
  - Mailing lists, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Sample forms (Box 1)
  - Student list, 1942-1945 (Box 1)
  - Suggested courses (Box 1)
- Program Files
  The Program Files series is arranged chronologically by program year. Each year's files contain bulletins sent from the Office of Education, correspondence between that office and Duke University, forms and reports, a miscellaneous folder, purchase orders which detail financial accounts, and a folder on each of the classes offered during that time, including those cancelled or denied authorization.
  - 1940-1941 (Box 1)
    - Bulletins (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Forms and reports (Box 1)
    - Courses (Box 1)
  - 1941-1942
    - Bulletins (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Forms and reports (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Purchase orders, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Courses, 13 folders (Box 2)
    - Courses, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - 1942-1943
    - Bulletins (Box 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Forms and reports (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Purchase orders (Box 3)
    - Courses, 16 folders (Box 4)
  - 1943-1944
    - Bulletins, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Forms and reports (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Purchase orders (Box 4)
    - Courses, 1 folder (Box 4)
    - Courses, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - 1944-1945
    - Bulletins (Box 5)
    - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Forms and reports (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Purchase orders (Box 5)
    - Courses, 14 folders (Box 5)